Learning-SICP学习小组
倾情制作
计算机程序的构造和解释
翻译&&时间轴
张大伟
（DreamAndDead）
压制&&特效
邓雄飞
（Dysprosium）
校对
邓雄飞
特别感谢
裘宗燕教授
流 II
PROFESSOR: OK, well, we've been looking at streams,
教授：上节课 我们介绍了流
this signal processing way of putting systems together.
按照信号处理的方式来组织系统
And remember, the key idea is that
要记住的是 关键点在于
we decouple
我们分离开
the apparent order of events in our programs
程序中 事件表面上的顺序
from the actual order of events in the computer.
与机器中的实际计算顺序
And that means that we can start
那就意味着 我们可以
dealing with very long streams
着手处理非常长的流
and only having to generate the elements on demand.
并且只有在需要的时候才生成其中的元素
That sort of on-demand computation
这种按需计算的方式
is built into the stream's data structure.
是内建在流的数据结构中的
So if we have a very long stream,
即使这个流非常之长
we only compute what we need.
我们只计算所需要的
The things only get computed when we actually ask for them.
只有当我们要求的时候 新的数据才会生成
Well, what are examples?
要举个什么样的例子呢？
Are they actually asking for them?
这个“按需”是什么个情况呢？
For instance, we might
举个例子
might ask for the n-th element of a stream.
我们可能会想要一个流中的第N个元素
Here's a procedure that computes the n-th element of a stream.
这个过程可以用于计算流的第N个元素
An integer n,
一个参数为索引N
the n-th element of some stream s,
另一个参数是流S
and we just recursively walk down the stream.
递归遍历这个流即可求解
And if n is 0, we compute the head.
如果N为0 我们就计算头部分
Otherwise, it's the n-th the minus 1 element
否则 就在流的尾部分
of the stream.
查找第N-1个元素
Those two are just like for Lisp, but the difference
看起来是Lisp中很普通的编程方式 但是不同的是
is those elements aren't going to get computed
直到我们不断遍历 取得相继的N个元素
until we walk down, taking successive n-ths.
这些元素才被计算出来
So that's one way that the stream elements might get forced.
这是这些流元素可能被FORCE的一种方式
And another way,
另外一种方式则是
here's a little procedure that prints a stream.
这里有个简单的过程 用来打印一个流
We say print a stream,
它的定义是
so to print a stream s.
过程PRINT-STREAM的定义是
Well, what do we do? We'll
我们要怎么做呢？
We print the head of the stream,
先打印流的头部分
and that will cause the head to be computed.
流的头部分在这时就被计算出来
And then we recursively print stream the tail of the stream.
然后我们再递归地打印流的尾部分
And if we're already done,
完成以后
maybe we have to return something about the message done.
就返回一个的表示完成的消息 “DONE”
OK, and then so if you make a stream,
如果你构造了一个流
you could say here's the stream, this very long stream.
这个流非常的长
And then you say print the stream,
当你调用这个过程
and the elements of the stream will get computed successively
流中的元素会随着PRINT-STREAM的调用
as that print calls them.
而被依次计算出来
They won't get all computed initially.
不会在一开始就全部计算出来
So in this way, we can
正因为如此 我们能够
So in this way, we can deal with some very long streams.
我们能够处理非常长的流
Well, how long can a stream be?
多长呢？
Well, it can be infinitely long.
可以是无限长
Let's look at an example here on the computer.
我们在计算机上实践一下
I could walk up to this computer, and I could say--
我可以在计算机前输入
how about we'll define the stream of integers starting with some number N,
我先定义一个函数 (INTEGERS-FROM N)
the stream of positive integers starting with some number n.
用于生成一个从N开始的正整数流
And that's cons-stream of n onto the integers from one more.
也就是 (CONS-STREAM N (INTEGERS-FROM (+ N 1))))
So there are the integers.
这样就我们要的全部整数
Then I could say let's get all the integers.
现在我来尝试得到所有的整数
define the stream of integers to be the integers starting with 1.
(DEFINE INTEGERS (INTEGERS-FROM 1))
And now if I say something like
如果现在我执行 (NTH-STREAM 20 INTEGERS)
what's the what's the 20th integer.
来查看第20个元素
So it's 21 because we start counting at 0.
得到21 因为索引是从0开始的
Or I can do more complicated things.
或者我们来点更复杂的
Let me to define a little predicate here.
我再来定义一个谓词
How about define no-seven.
谓词NO-SEVEN用来检测是否为7的倍数
It's going to test an integer,
它的判定方法是这样的：
and it's going to say it's not.
如果整数X不是7的倍数
I take the remainder of x by 7,
我取X除7的余数
I don't get 0.
余数不应该为0
And then I could say define the integers with no sevens
这时用NO-SEVEN这个谓词
take all the integers and filter them to have no sevens.
过滤全部的整数
So now I've got the stream of all the integers
这样我就得到了所有的
that are not divisible by seven.
不是7的倍数的整数构成的流
So if I say what's the 100th integer
如果我问 这些不是7的倍数的整数中
and the list not divisible by seven,
的第100个数是多少？
I get 117.
结果是117
Or if I'd like to say well, I could say ah.
或者我也可以问
well, gee, what are all of them?
这个流的所有元素都是些什么？
So I could say print stream all these integers with no seven,
我可以用(PRINT-STREAM NS)来尝试打印这个流
it goes off printing.
它就会输出个不停
You may have to wait a very long time to see them all.
你可能需要等上很久才能得到全部结果
Well, you can start asking, gee,
你可能会问了
you know, is it really true that this data structure
这个数据结构
with the integers is really all the integers?
真的全部是由整数构成的吗？
And let me draw a picture of that program I just wrote.
现在我画一个图来演示下刚写的那个程序
Here's the, right, here's the definition of the integers again that I just typed in,
这是我刚才键入的整数定义
Right it's a cons of the first integer under the integer starting with the rest.
它是一个由第一个整数和由下一个整数生成的流 所构成的序对
Now, we can make a picture of that and see what it looks like.
现在我们画个图来看看它到底是什么样
Conceptually, what I have is a box
从概念上来说 这应该是一个盒子
that's the integer starting with n.
这个盒子是(INTEGER-FROM N)
It takes in some number n,
它接受一个参数N
and it's going to return a stream of--
然后返回一个流
this infinite stream of all integers starting with n.
这个无穷流表示从N开始的所有整数
And what do I do?
我要做什么呢？
Well, this is an integers-from box.
呃 这个是INT-FROM盒子
What's it got in it?
里面是什么样子呢？
Well, it takes in this n,
取得参数N之后
and it increments it.
将其 +1
And then it puts the result into recursively another integer's from box.
然后把结果递归地传递给另一个INT-FROM盒子
It takes the result of that and the original n
把这个盒子的结果和最初的N
and puts those together with a cons
用CONS组合起来
and forms a stream.
就形成了一个流
So that's a picture of that program I wrote. And this is a ...
我刚才写的那个过程 画出来就是这样子
Let's see. These kind of diagrams we first saw
我们看到的这类图像
drawn by Peter Henderson,
首先是由Peter Henderson提出的
the same guy who did the Escher language.
也就是前面课程中绘图语言的发明者
We call them Henderson diagrams.
我们把这种图叫做Henderson图
And the convention here is that you put these things together.
画这种图需要遵守一定的约定
And the solid lines are things coming out are streams,
这些实线代表输出的流
and dotted lines are initial values going in.
这些虚线则是初始的输入值
So this one has the shape of--
而这个图描述的形状是——
it takes in some integer, some initial value,
它会取一个整数作为初始值
and outputs a stream.
然后输出一个流
Again, you can ask. You know it's really
现在 你可能又要问了
Is that data structure integers really all the integers?
那个INTEGERS的数据结构真的全部都是整数吗？
Alright? Or is it is something that's cleverly arranged
或者它只是经过了精心组织
so that whenever you look for an integer
以至于总可以在其中找到
you find it there?
我们需要的那个整数？
That's sort of a philosophical question, right?
这有点像个哲学问题 不是么？
If something is there
如果有一个东西
whenever you look, is it really there or not?
你不去观测它 能否知道它“存在”呢？
It's sort of the same sense in which
这就有点像
the money in your savings account is in the bank.
你在银行中的存款那样
Well
好吧
let me do another example.
我们再来看一个例子
Umm, Gee, we started the course
这门课的第一节课
with an algorithm from Alexandria,
我们就讲了一个来自于亚历山大的算法
which was Heron of Alexandria's algorithm
来自亚历山大的Heron提出的
for computing the square root.
一个用于计算平方根的算法
Let's take a look at another Alexandrian algorithm.
现在再来看一个 同样来自于亚力山大的算法
This one is Eratosthenes method for
这个被称为Eratosthenes算法的方法
for computing all of the primes.
用于计算所有的质数
It is called the Sieve of Eratosthenes.
它被称为Eratosthenes筛法
And what you do is you start out,
它是这样的 一开始
and you list all the integers,
先列举所有的整数
say, starting with 2.
从2开始
And then you take the first integer, and you say,
然后取第一个整数
and you say, oh, that's prime.
然后你发现 哦 2是一个质数
And then you go look at the rest,
然后你考察剩余的整数
and you cross out all the things divisible by 2.
划掉其中可以被2整除的数
So I cross out this and this and this.
我把这个划掉 还有这个 这个
This takes a long time
有点费时
because I have to do it for all of the integers.
我要对所有的整数进行这样的操作
So I go through the entire list of integers,
我遍历整个整数表
crossing the ones divisible by 2.
划掉所有被2整除的数
And now when I finish with all of the integers,
所有的整数都操作完后
I go back and look and say what am I left with?
回过头再来看还剩些什么
Well, the first thing that starts there is 3.
好的 下一个数就是3了
So 3 is a prime.
3也是一个质数
And now I go back through what I'm left with,
现在 我会继续在剩下的数中
and I cross out all the things divisible by 3.
划掉所有被3整除的数
So let's see, 9 and 15 and 21 and 27 and 33 and so on.
划掉 9、15、21、27、33 等等
I won't finish.
我就不往下划了
Then I see what I'm left with.
然后看看我们还剩下什么
And the next one I have is 5.
而下一个就是5了
Now I can through the rest,
我又遍历剩下的数
and I find the first one that's divisible by 5.
找到第一个能被5整除的数
I cross out from the remainder all the ones that are divisible by 5.
把剩下的能被5整除的数都划掉
And I did that,
做完这个之后
and then I go through and find 7.
下一个数就是7
Go through all the rest,
再遍历剩下的数
cross out things divisible 7,
划掉所有被7整除的数
and I keep doing that forever.
然后一直这样下去
And when I'm done,
全部结束的时候
what I'm left with is a list of all the primes.
我也就得到了所有的质数
So that's the Sieve of Eratosthenes.
这就是Eratosthenes筛法
Let's look at it as a computer program.
我们来看下实际代码
It's a procedure called sieve.
这个过程命名为SIEVE
Now, I just write what I did.
这是对应的代码
I'll say to sieve some stream s.
SIEVE过程 以一个流S为参数
I'm going to build a stream
返回一个新的流
whose first element is the head of this.
新的流的头部分 就是流S的头部分
Remember, I always found the first thing I was left with,
回忆一下 我总是取剩下的数中的第一个
and the rest of it is the result of taking the tail of S,
而尾部分则是把流S的尾部分
filtering it to throw away all the things
过滤掉所有
that are divisible by the head of S,
能被S头部分整除的数
and now sieving the result.
然后再对结果筛选
That's just what I did.
这个代码就是这样
And now to get the infinite stream of times,
现在 为了得到由质数构成的无穷流
we just sieve all the integers starting from 2.
我们对从2开始的整数流进行SIEVE
Let's try that.
我们来实践一下
We can actually do it.
实际上 我们可以在计算机中运行
I typed in the definition of sieve before, I hope,
我希望我已经预先输入过SIEVE的定义了
so I can say something like
所以我可以定义
define the primes to be
我可以把PRIMES定义为
the result of sieving the integers starting with 2.
(SIEVE (INTEGERS-FROM 2))
So now I've got this list of primes.
现在我就得到了质数构成的表
That's all of the primes, right?
这样就得到了所有的质数 对吧？
So, if for example, what's the 20th prime in that list?
比如我可以问 第20个质数是什么？
73.
结果是73
See, and that little pause,
那个短促的停顿
it was only at the point
这是因为
when I started asking for the 20th prime
在我询问第20个元素时
is that it started computing.
它才进行实际的计算
Or I can say here
在这里 我也可以要求
Or I can say here let's look at all of the primes.
打印所有的质数
And there it goes computing all of the primes.
解释器就开始计算并打印所有的质数
Of course, it will take a while
得花上好一会儿
again if I want to look at all of them,
才能打赢完整
so let's stop it.
所以先把它停掉
Let me draw you a picture of that.
让我来画图演示一下
Well, I've got a picture of that.
我已经画好了
What's that program really look like?
这个过程的图形应该是什么样子呢？
Again, some practice with these diagrams,
用这类图形的约定来说
I have a sieve box.
我有一个叫SIEVE的盒子
How does sieve work?
它是如何运作的呢？
It takes in a stream.
它以一个流作为输入
It splits off the head from the tail.
分离流的头、尾部分
And the first thing that's going to come out of the sieve
从SIEVE盒子出来的第一个东西
is the head of the original stream.
就是原来流的头部分
Then it also takes the head and uses that.
头部分同样也用于这个盒子
It takes the stream. It filters the tail
这个盒子会过滤流的尾部分
It filters the tail and uses the head to filter for nondivisibility.
过滤的依据是 能否被头部分整除
It takes the result of nondivisibility
过滤得到的不可整除的那些数
and puts it through another sieve box
再放入另一个SIEVE盒子
and puts the result together.
然后把它们组合输出
So you can think of this sieve a filter,
你可以把SIEVE想象为一个过滤器
but notice that it's an infinitely recursive filter.
只不过它是一个无穷递归的过滤器
Because inside the sieve box
这是因为在SIEVE盒子中
is another sieve box,
还有另外一个SIEVE盒子
and inside that is another sieve box and another sieve box.
内部的盒子里面还有另外一个SIEVE盒子
So you see we start getting some very powerful things.
我们现在逐渐有了非常厉害的能力
We're starting to mix this signal processing view of the world
我们开始把 信号处理的方法
with things like recursion that come from computation.
和计算中的递归结合在一起 来建模世界
And there are all sorts of interesting things you can do that are like this.
还有很多像是这样的事
All right, any questions?
好的 有什么问题吗？
OK, let's take a break.
好吧 那我们休息一下
[音乐]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
讲师：哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
流 II
Well, we've been looking at a couple
我们已经看了
of examples of stream programming.
好几个流式程序设计的例子
All the stream procedures that we've looked at so far
我们目前接触到的流过程
have the same kind of character.
都有一个共同的特征
We've been writing these recursive procedures
这些过程总是递归地
that kind of generate these stream elements one at a time
一次生成一个元素
and put them together in cons-streams.
再用CONS-STREAM连接起来
So we've been thinking a lot about generators.
因此 我们一直把它当作是生成器
There's another way to think about stream processing,
还有一种思考流式程序设计的方式
and that's to focus not on programs that sort of
我们不认为程序是
process these elements as you walk down the stream,
沿着流逐一处理元素
but on things that kind of process the streams all at once.
而是一下子处理了整个流
To show you what I mean, let me start by defining
我先来定义两个非常有用的过程
two procedures that will come in handy.
来帮助我说明
The first one's called add streams.
第一个过程是ADD-STREAMS
Add streams takes two streams:
它接受两个流作为参数
s1 and s2.
S1和S2
And it's going to produce a stream
它生成一个新的流
whose elements are the are the corresponding sums
其元素是两个流相应位置元素的和
We just sort of add them element-wise.
相当于是“按元素”的加
If either stream is empty,
如果其中一个流是空的
we just return the other one.
我们就返回另一个
Otherwise, we're going to make a new stream
否则 我们就构建一个新的流
whose head is the sum of the two heads
新流的头部分是两个流头部分之和
whose tail
而新流的尾部分
is the result of recursively adding the tails.
则是递归地加和尾部分
So that will produce the element-wise sum of two streams.
这就会产生“按元素”地加的效果
And then another useful thing to have around is scale stream.
另一个过程是SCALE-STREAM
Scale stream takes some constant number in a stream s
SCALE-STREAM有两个参数 常数C和流S
and is going to produce the stream
结果生成的流
of elements of s multiplied by this constant.
就是将流S的所有元素乘上了C
And that's easy, that's just a map
这很简单 就是一个MAP
of the function of an element that multiplies it by the constant,
用到的函数是 X*C
and we map that down the stream.
把这个函数MAP于整个流
So given those two,
有了这两个过程
let me show you what I mean by programs that
我来给你们解释 什么叫做
that operate on streams all at once.
“一下子处理整个流”
Let's look at this.
我们来看这个
Suppose I write this.
假设这样
I say define--  I'll call it ones-- to be cons-stream of 1 onto ones.
(DEFINE ONES (CONS-STREAM 1 ONES))
What's that?
这是什么？
That's going to be an infinite stream of ones
这是一个表示无穷个1的流
because the first thing is 1.
因为第一个元素是1
And the tail of it is a thing
尾部分则是这样的
whose first thing is 1
它的头部分是1
whose tail is a thing
它的尾部分
whose first thing is 1
的头部分又为1
and so on and so on.
以此类推
So that's an infinite stream of ones.
这就是无穷个1的流
And now using that,
现在根据ONES
let me give you another definition of the integers.
我再给出另一种定义整数的方式
We can define the integers to be--
(DEFINE INTEGERS
well, the first integer we'll take to be 1,
当然 第一个数是1
his cons-stream of 1 onto the element-wise sum
(CONS-STREAM 1 (ADD-STREAM
onto add streams of the integers to ones.
INTEGERS ONES)))
The integers are a thing
整数流是这样的：
whose first element is 1,
它的第一个元素是1
and the rest of them you get
而其余部分则是
by taking those integers and incrementing each one by one.
依次把每个整数加1
So the second element of the integers
因此 整数流的第二个元素则是
is the first element of the integers incremented by one.
整数流的第一个元素加1
And the rest of that is the next one,
下一个数又要加1
and the third element of that
第三个元素则是
is the same as the first element of the tail of the integers
INTEGER流尾部分的第一个元素
incremented by one,
加1
which is the same as the
这也就相当于
first element of the original integers incremented by one
最初整数流的第一个元素加1
and incremented by one again and so on.
然后再加1 以此类推
That looks pretty suspicious.
这看起来有点匪夷所思
See, notice that it works
这样的过程可以正常运行
because of delay.
关键在于延时求值
See, this looks like-- let's take a look at ones.
我们来看这个ONES
This looks like it couldn't even be processed
这看起来根本不可能
because it's suddenly saying
因为它突然说
in order to know what ones is,
在定义ONES的时候
I say it's cons-stream of something onto ones.
发现它依赖于它本身
The reason that works
它之所以可以运行是因为
because of that very sneaky hidden delay in there.
这里暗中隐藏着延时求值
Because what this really is,
这个代码实际上是
remember, cons-stream is just an abbreviation.
回忆下 CONS-STREAM是只是一个缩写
This really is
实际上则是
cons of 1 onto delay of ones.
(CONS 1 (DELAY ONES))
So how does that work?
它又是怎么运作的呢？
You say I'm going to define ones.
你想要定义ONES
First I see what ones is supposed to be defined as.
我来看看ONES要被定义成什么样
Well, ones is supposed to be defined as
ONES被定义为一个序对
a cons whose first part is 1
其CAR部分为1
and the second part is,
而CDR部分则是
well, it's a promise to compute something
是一个计算某物的PROMISE
that I don't worry about yet.
我现在还不用关心
So it doesn't bother me that at the point
所以虽然这时ONES还没有定义
I do this definition, ones isn't defined.
但对我并不造成什么影响
Having run the definition, now ones is defined.
一旦运行了整个定义 ONES就被定义了
So that when I go and look at the tail of it, it's defined.
所以 访问它尾部的时候 它就有定义了
It's very sneaky.
这一点非常隐讳
And an integer is the same way.
整数流的定义也是如此
I can refer to integers here because
我可以在这里引用INTEGERS是因为
hidden way down-- because of this cons-stream.
是因为这个CONS-STREAM的缘故
It's the cons-stream of 1
用CONS-STREAM把1
onto something that I don't worry that yet.
和一个不立即需要的东西组合起来
So I don't look at it, and I don't notice that integers isn't defined
所以我在运行INTEGERS的定义的时候
at the point where I try and run the definition.
并不会发现INTEGER没有定义过
OK, let me draw a picture of that integers thing
听上去非常玄乎
because it still maybe seems a little bit shaky.
让我用图像来演示一下INTEGERS的原理
What do I do? Uh...
怎么画呢？
I've got the stream of ones,
首先是ONES这个流
and that sort of comes in
它作为参数输入
comes in and goes into an adder
进入一个加法器
that's going to be this add streams thing.
进行流的加法运算
And that goes in-- that's going to put out the integers.
输出则是整数流INTEGERS
And the other thing that goes into the adder here
这里 这个整数流又重新进入加法器
is the integer, so there's a little feedback loop.
形成了一个小型的反馈回路
And all I need to start it off
我需要在某处接入最初的ONES
is someplace I've got a stick that initial 1.
才能让它生效
In a real signal processing thing,
在真实的信号处理中
this might be a delay element with that was initialized to 1.
这里是一个被初始化为1的延时元件
But there's a picture of that ones program.
这就是ONES程序的图示
And in fact, that looks a lot like--
事实上 这个非常像
if you've seen real signal block diagram things,
如果你见过真正的信号方块图的话
that looks a lot like accumulators,
这个图形非常像累加器
finite state accumulators.
有穷状态累加器
And in fact, we can modify this a little bit
事实上 我们可以稍加修改
to change this into something that integrates a stream
就可以让它对一个流做积分
or a finite state accumulator,
或者说是有穷状态累加器
however you like to think about it.
你怎么认为都可以
So instead of the ones coming in and getting out the integers,
现在 不再是输入ONES 输出INTEGERS
what we'll do is
我们要做的是
say there's a stream s coming in,
这里有一个流S为输入
and we're going to get out the integral of this.
我们要计算这个流的积分
successive values of that,
也就是累加这个流的值
and it looks almost the same.
这看起来几乎就是一样的
The only thing we're going to do is
我们要做的就是
when s comes in here,
当S从这里输入时
before we just add it in
在把它求和之前
we're going to multiply it by some number dt.
先将其乘以dt
And now what we have here, this is exactly the same thing.
剩下的就不用改了
We have a box,
我们就得到了一个盒子
which is an integrator.
一个积分器
And it takes in a stream s,
对一个流S进行积分
and instead of 1 here,
把这里的1替换为
we can put the additional value for the integral.
该积分的初始值
And that one looks very much like a
这个看起来就非常像
a signal processing block diagram program.
信号处理中的方框图了
In fact, here's the procedure that looks exactly like that.
事实上 这个图示对应的是这样一个过程
Find the integral of a stream.
对一个流进行积分
So an integral's going to take a stream
INTEGRAL函数接收一个流
Sand produce a new stream,
返回一个新的流
and it takes in an initial value and some time constant.
它还接收一个初始值和某个时间常量
And what do we do?
然后呢？
Well, we internally define this thing int,
首先在内部定义一个流INT
and we make this internal name
之所以要给它一个内部名字
so we can feed it back, loop it around itself.
原因在于可以使它反馈 以形成循环
And int is defined to be
INT的定义是
something that starts out at the initial value,
一个以INITIA-VALUE开始的流
and the rest of it is gotten by adding together.
而其余的元素则是把它们加起来
We take our input stream, scale it by dt,
我们把输入流乘以dt
and add that to int.
然后和INT相加
And now we'll return from all that the value of integral is this thing int.
整个INTEGRAL函数的结果就是这个INT
And we use this internal definition syntax so we could
我们使用这种内部定义的语法
write a little internal definition that refers to itself.
是为了可以在内部引用它自己
Well, there are all sorts of things we can do.
我们还可以做更多的事情
Let's try this one.
来看这个
how about the Fibonacci numbers.
斐波那契数
You can say define fibs.
(DEFINE FIBS
Well, what are the Fibonacci numbers?
斐波那契数是什么呢？
They're something that starts out with 0,
它从0开始
and the next one is 1.
下一个是1
And the rest of the Fibonacci numbers are gotten by
的其余的斐波那契数是通过
adding the Fibonacci numbers to their own tail.
把它们的尾部分求和而得来
There's a definition of the Fibonacci numbers.
这样来定义斐波那契数
How does that work?
这是如何运作的呢？
Well, we start off,
我们来试试
and someone says compute for us the Fibonacci numbers,
假如开始计算斐波那契数
and we're going to tell you it starts out with 0 and 1.
首先告诉你 它以0和1开始
And everything after the 0 and 1
而0和1之后的数则是
is gotten by summing two streams.
通过加和两个流而得
One is the fibs themselves,
一个流是FIBS本身
and the other one is the tail of the fibs.
另一个是FIBS的尾部分
So if I know that these start out with 0 and 1,
如果我知道这是以0和1起始的
I know that the fibs now start out with 0 and 1,
我就能知道 FIBS是以0和1起始的
and the tail of the fibs start out with 1.
那么 FIBS的尾部分则应该以1开始
So as soon as I know that,
一旦我知道了这点
I know that the next one here is 0 plus 1 is 1,
我就知道 FIBS的下一个数就是0+1=1
and that tells me that the next one here is 1
它也同样告诉我这里是1
and the next one here is 1.
这里也是1
And as soon as I know that,
知道了这些之后
I know that the next one is 2.
我就知道下一个是2
So the next one here is 2 and the next one here is 2.
这里是2 这里也是2
And this is 3.
下一个是3
This one goes to 3,
这里是3
and this is 5.
这里是5
So it's a perfectly sensible definition.
这个定义完全说得通
It's a one-line definition.
这个定义只有一行
And again, I could walk over to the computer
当然 我也可以在计算机中
and type that in, exactly that,
原原本本地键入计算机中
and then say print stream the Fibonacci numbers,
然后要求输出斐波那契数
and they all come flying out.
然后它就会不断输出
See, this is a lot like learning about recursion again.
这又像是在学习递归
Instead of thinking that recursive procedures,
过程可以被递归定义
we have recursively defined data objects.
我们也可以递归地定义数据对象
But that shouldn't surprise you at all,
但你们一点儿不应该感到吃惊
because by now, you should be coming to really believe
因为现在 你们应该真正相信
that there's no difference really between procedures and data.
过程与数据之间没有区别
In fact, in some sense,
事实上 就某种意义上来说
the underlying streams are procedures sitting there,
流也是由过程来实现的
although we don't think of them that way.
只不过我们不把它看做过程而已
So the fact that we have recursive procedures,
因此既然我们有递归过程
well, then it should be natural that we have recursive data, too.
那么 有递归数据也就不足为奇了
OK, well, this is all pretty neat.
虽然流非常简洁
Unfortunately, there are problems that streams aren't going to solve.
但不幸的是 有些问题流无法解决
Let me show you one of them.
我来举个例子
See, in the same way, let's imagine that we're
同样地 我们来想象一下
building an analog computer to solve some differential equation
我们正在构建求解微分方程的模拟计算机
like, say, we want to solve the equation y prime dy dt is y squared,
比如求解方程 y' = y^2
and I'm going to give you some initial value.
我会给你一个初值
I'll tell you y of 0 equals 1.
y(0) = 1
Let's say dt is equal to something.
dt = .0001
Now, in the old days,
很久之前
people built analog computers to solve these kinds of things.
就有人构建模拟计算机 来解决这类问题
And the way you do that is really simple.
原理非常简单
You get yourself an integrator,
你首先需要一个积分器
like that one, an integrator box.
比如这个INT盒子
And we put in the initial value y of 0 is 1.
我们设定初始值 y(0) = 1
And now if we feed something in and get something out,
现在如果我们送入一个输入 就会得到输出
we'll say, gee, what we're getting out is the answer.
输出的结果就是y
And what we're going to feed in is the derivative,
输入的是y的导数
and the derivative is supposed to be the square of the answer.
在这里 导数 y' = y^2
So if we take these values and map using square,
如果我们用MAP把SQUARE映射在这些值上
and if I feed this around,
然后把这个引过来
that's how I build a block diagram
这个方块图
for an analog computer that solves this differential equation.
就是用于求解这个微分方程的模拟计算机
Now, what we'd like to do is write a stream
现在我们用代码
program that looks exactly like that.
来表示下这个过程
And what do I mean exactly like that?
这个图究竟表示的是什么呢？
Well, I'd say define y to be the integral
(DEFINE Y
of dy starting at 1 with 0.001 as a time step.
(INTEGRAL DY 1 .001))
And I'd like to say that says this.
接下来
And then I'd like to say, well, dy is gotten by mapping the square along y.
通过MAP SQUARE 来表示dy
So define dy to be map square along y.
(DEFINE DY (MAP SQUARE Y))
So there's a stream description of this analog computer,
这就是这个模拟计算机的流式描述
and unfortunately, it doesn't work.
不幸的是 它并不起效
And you can see why it doesn't work
你也可以发现这是为什么
because when I come in and say define y
因为我把Y定义为
to be the integral of dy
DY 的积分
it says, oh, the integral of what-- huh?
它会问 对什么的积分？
Oh, that's undefined.
没定义啊
So I can't write this definition before I've written this one.
所以这个定义必须写在这个定义的后面
On the other hand, if I try and write this one first,
另一方面 如果先定义了dy
it says, oh, I define y to be the map of square along what?
定义为 (MAP SQUARE 某个东西)
Oh, that's not defined yet.
这个也还没有定义
So I can't write this one first, and I can't write that one first.
我既不能先写这个 又不能先写那个
So I can't quite play this game.
这个游戏就没法玩了
Well, is there a way out?
怎样来解决呢？
See, we can do that with ones.
我们可以用ONES来解决
See, over here, we did this thing ones,
所以 我们在这里定义的ONES
and we were able to define ones in terms of ones because
我们之所以可以使用ONES来定义ONES
of this delay that was built inside
这是因为其中的延时求值
because cons-stream had a delay.
CONS-STREAM是延时求值的
Now, why's it sensible?
那么 这又为什么说得通呢？
Why's it sensible for cons-stream to be built with this delay?
为什么CONS-STREAM是延时求值的是合理的呢？
The reason is that cons-stream can do a useful thing
原因在于 CONS-STREAM不需要其尾部分
without looking at its tail.
就可以完成有意义的事
See, if I say
比如我说
this is cons-stream of 1 onto something
这个是1和某个东西组成的流
without knowing anything about something,
虽然我对它一无所知
I know that the stream starts off with 1.
但我却知道整个流是以1开始的
That's why it was sensible to build something like cons-stream.
所以用CONS-STREAM来构造是有意义的
So we put a delay in there,
我们在这里放了一个DELAY
and that allows us to have this sort of self-referential definition.
这就使得我们能够进行某种自引用的定义
Well, integral is a little bit the same way.
INTEGRAL也可以用这种方式来解决
See, notice for an integral, I can--
注意 对于INTEGRAL来说 我可以
let's go back and look at integral for a second.
让我们回过头来再看看INTEGRAL的定义
See, notice integral,
求积分的时候
it makes sense to say what's the first thing in the integral
知道INTEGRAL的第一个元素是合理的
without knowing the stream that you're integrating.
尽管还不知道整个流是什么样的
Because the first thing in the integral
这是因为INTEGRAL中第一个元素
is always going to be the initial value that you're handed.
总会是你传递过来的INITIAL-VALUE
So integral could be a procedure like cons-stream.
所以INTEGRAL可以用CONS-STREAM来实现
You could define it,
我们可以定义它
and then even before it knows what it's supposed to be integrating,
甚至不用知道要积分的流是什么
it knows enough to say what its initial value is.
只需要知道初始值是什么就行了
So we can make a smarter integral,
INTEGRAL还可以修改得更为智能
which is aha, you're going to give me a stream to integrate
我们给它一个待积分的流
and an initial value,
以及一个初值
but I really don't have to look at that stream that I'm supposed to integrate
直到你要求沿着这个流求解积分时
until you ask me to work down the stream.
我才关心这个流是什么
In other words, integral can be like cons-stream,
换句话说INTEGRAL可以像CONS-STREAM一样
and you can expect that there's going to be a delay around its integrand.
你可以认为INTEGRAL被放在DELAY之中
And we can write that.
我们这样修改
Here's a procedure that does that.
这个过程是像这样的
Another version of integral,
这是另一个版本的INTEGRAL
and this is almost like the previous one,
这个跟之前的版本非常相似
except the stream it's going to get in
只不过作为参数的流
is going to expect to be a delayed object.
必须要是一个延时对象
And how does this integral work?
这个INTEGRAL又是如何运作的呢？
Well, the little thing it's going to define inside of itself
我们在内部定义的INT则是
says on the cons-stream,
用CONS-STREAM构造一个流
the initial value is the initial value,
初值还是INITIAL-VALUE
but only inside of that cons-stream,
但是在CONS-STREAM中
and remember, there's going to be a hidden delay inside here.
要注意 这里面有个隐藏的DELAY
Only inside of that cons-stream will I start looking at
只有在这个CONS-STREAM的内部
what the actual delayed object is.
我才会查看延时对象的实际内容
So my answer is the first thing's the initial value.
所以 答案的第一个元素将会是初值
If anybody now asks me for my tail,
如果有人想访问我的尾部分
at that point,
此时
I'm going to force that delayed object--
我会FORCE该延迟对象
and I'll call that s--
把结果记作S
and I do the add streams.
然后再进行ADD-STREAMS
So this is an integral which is sort of like cons-stream.
这个INTEGRAL就有点像CONS-STREAM
It's not going to actually try and see what you handed it
直到你确实需要知道第一个元素的时候
as the thing to integrate until you look past the first element.
它才会去查看DELAYED-S是什么
And if we do that
如果这样的话
and we can make this work,
也就能求解 y' = y^2 了
all we have to do here is
这里我们只需要
define y to the integral of delay of y, of delay of dy.
把Y定义为对延时对象DY的积分
So y is going to be
所以Y的定义就变成了
the integral of delay of dy starting at 1,
(INTEGRAL (DELAY DY) 1 .001)
and now this will work.
这样一来就可以了
Because I type in the definition of y,
因为我输入Y的定义
and that says, oh, I'm supposed to use the integral of
它是某个东西的积分
something I don't care about right now because it's a delay.
但这是个延迟对象 我现在还不用关心
And these things, now you define dy.
这之后 再定义DY
Now, y is defined.
现在Y就有定义了
So when I define dy,
所以我在定义DY时
it can see that definition for y.
它可以知道Y的定义
Everything is now started up.
一切都正常了
Both streams have their first element.
两个流都有第一个元素
And then when I start mapping down,
当我不断取得下一个元素
looking at successive elements,
沿着流做MAP运算时
both y and dy are defined.
Y和DY都被定义过了
So there's a little game you can play that goes a little bit beyond
所以为了继续这个游戏 我们不能仅仅
just using the delay that's hidden inside streams.
只使用隐藏在流中的DELAY
Questions?
有问题么？
OK, let's take a break.
休息一下吧
[音乐]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
讲师：哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
流 II
Well, just before the break, um..
上节课的最后
I'm not sure if you noticed it,
不知道你们注意到没有
but something nasty started to happen.
事情正变得糟糕起来
We've been going along with the streams
我们讲了很多关于 流
and divorcing time in the programs from time in the computers,
以及分离程序中的时间和计算机中的时间
and all that divorcing got hidden inside the streams.
这些分离都被隐藏在流中了
And then at the very end, we saw that sometimes
上节课快结束时我们发现
in order to really take advantage of this method,
为了真正发挥这种方法的优势
you have to pull out other delays.
我们需要另外的DELAY
You have to write some explicit delays
不只需要隐藏在CONS-STREAM中的DELAY
that are not hidden inside that cons-stream.
还需要显式地使用DELAY
And I did a very simple example with differential equations,
我只是用微分方程举了一个很简单的例子
but if you have some very complicated system
但是如果你有一个非常复杂的系统
with all kinds of self-loops,
里面充斥着各种各样的自循环
it becomes very, very difficult to
那就很难再发现
see where you need those delays.
在什么地方需要额外的DELAY了
And if you leave them out by mistake,
假如你一不小心漏了一个
it becomes very, very difficult to see why the thing maybe isn't working.
就很难发现程序为什么不起效
So that's kind of mess,
这是一种混乱
that by getting this power and allowing us to use delay,
让我们能够使用DELAY
we end up with some very complicated programming sometimes,
有时却会让程序设计变得非常复杂
because it can't all be hidden inside the streams.
因为它们不能完全隐藏在流中
Well, is there a way out of that?
那么 有没有什么解决方案呢？
Yeah, there is a way out of that.
所幸的是 有
We could change the language so that
我们可以修改整个语言
all procedures acted like cons-stream,
使得所有的过程都表现得像CONS-STREAM一样
so that every procedure automatically
这样所有的过程都会
has an implicit delay around its arguments.
自动、隐式地为它的参数加上DELAY
And what would that mean?
这是什么意思呢？
That would mean when you call a procedure,
就是说 当你调用一个过程时
the arguments wouldn't get evaluated.
参数并不会立即求值
Instead, they'd only be evaluated when you need them,
只有在需要被求值的时候 它们才会被求值
so they might be passed off to some other procedure,
它们也可能被传递给其它的过程
which wouldn't evaluate them either.
而这个过程也不会求值这些参数
So all these procedures would be passing promises around.
因此这些过程间传递的是PROMISE
And then finally maybe when you finally got down
直到最后
to having to look at the value of something
你需要查看某个值的时候
that was handed to a primitive operator
可能是因为一个基本运算所需要
which you actually start calling in all those promises.
这是你才实际求值这些PROMISE
If we did that,
像这样修改语言之后
since everything would have a uniform delay,
由于所有的东西都是统一被延时的
then you wouldn't have to write any explicit delays,
就不需要任何显式的DELAY了
because it would be automatically built into the way the language works.
因为它自动地内建在语言之中了
Or another way to say that,
换句话来说
technically what I'm describing is what's called
从技术上来说 我所描述的
if we did that, our language would be
如果修改后的语言被称作
so-called normal-order evaluation language
所谓的“正则序求值”语言
versus what we've actually been working with,
这个跟我们一直使用的语言不同
which is called applicative order--  versus applicative-order evaluation.
我们所用的是“应用序求值”语言
And remember the substitution model for applicative order.
还记得应用序求值的代换模型吧
It says when you go and evaluate a combination,
当你求值一个组合式的时候
you find the values of all the pieces.
你需要先计算出每一个元素的值
You evaluate the arguments and then you
先求值所有的参数
substitute them in the body of the procedure.
再把它们代换入过程的体
Normal order says no, don't do that.
正则序则不是这样
What you do is effectively
你所做的则是
substitute in the body of the procedure,
直接将参数代换入过程的体
but instead of evaluating the arguments,
而不先对参数求值
you just put a promise to compute them there.
只是代换入了一个计算参数的PROMISE
Or another way to say that
换句话说就是
you take the expressions for the arguments, if you like,
把作为参数的整个表达式
and substitute them in the body of the procedure and go on,
直接代入过程的体进行代换
and never really simplify anything
在此之间从不进行任何化简
until you get down to a primitive operator.
直到遇到一个基本运算符
So that would be a normal-order language.
这就是所谓的正则序求值语言
Well, why don't we do that?
我们为什么不这样做呢？
Because if we did,
这样做了之后
we'd get all the advantages of delayed evaluation
我们就获得了延时求值的所有优点
with none of the mess.
而不会一片混乱
In fact, if we did that
事实上 如果我们这样做了之后
and cons was just a delayed procedure,
CONS也会是延时求值的
that would make cons the same as cons-stream.
就和CONS-STREAM一样
We wouldn't need streams at all
我们就不再需要流了
because lists would automatically be streams.
因为表自动成为了流
That's how lists would behave,
表和流有一样的行为
all data structures would behave that way.
所有的数据结构也会像那样
Everything would behave that way.
所有的都是
Right, You'd never really do any computation
直到需要答案的时候
until you actually needed the answer.
才会去实际的求值
You wouldn't have to worry about all these explicit annoying delays.
不必再担心 什么时候需要显式地标注DELAY
Well, why don't we do that?
为什么不这样做呢？
First of all, I should say people do do that.
首先 已经有人这样做过了
There's some very beautiful languages.
有一些十分优雅的语言
One of the very nicest is a language called Miranda,
其中最为人称道的是一门名为 Miranda 的语言
which is, um..
它是由
developed by David Turner at the University of Kent.
肯特大学的 David Turner 开发的
And that's how this language works.
它就是用这样的原理实现的
It's a normal-order language
Miranda是正则序求值语言
and its data structures,
它的数据结构
which look like lists, are actually streams.
看起来像表 实际上确实流
And you write ordinary procedures in Miranda,
你不需要任何特殊的功能
and they do these prime things and eight queens things,
就可以在Miranda中编写普通的过程
just without anything special.
来解决质数、八皇后这样的问题
It's all built in there.
这些都是语言的内建功能
But there's a price.
但这样做也要付出代价
Remember how we got here.
还记得我们为什么引入流了吗？
We're decoupling time in the programs from time in the machines.
我们分离了程序的时间和它实际执行的时间
And if we put delay,
如果我们引入了DELAY
that sort of decouples it everywhere,
这样就在所有的地方完成了解耦
not just in streams.
而不单单是在流中
Remember what we're trying to do.
我们的初衷是什么？
We're trying to think about programming as a way to specify processes.
我们把程序设计看做是指定计算过程
And if we give up too much time,
如果我们放弃了对时间的控制
our language becomes more elegant,
尽管语言变得优雅起来
but it becomes a little bit less expressive.
但是它的表达力却有所下降
There are certain distinctions that we can't draw.
这里面还有一些我们无法消除的区别
One of them, for instance, is iteration.
其中之一就是迭代
Remember this old procedure,
还记得这个程序吗？
iterative factorial,
迭代式的阶乘
that we looked at quite a long time ago.
这是我们很早之前就研究过的
Iterative factorial had a thing,
过程FACT-ITER
and it said there was an internal procedure,
有一个内部过程ITER
and there was a state which was a product and a counter,
它含有两个状态PRODUCT和COUNTER
and we iterate that going around the loop.
它们随着循环不断迭代
And we said that was an iterative procedure
之所以说这个过程是迭代的
because it didn't build up state.
是因为它没有创建新状态
And the reason it didn't build up state is
之所以没有创建新状态
because this iter that's called
是因为在调用ITER时
is just passing these things around to itself.
作为参数传递给它自己的始终是这些东西
Or in the substitution model that,
在代换模型中
you could see in the substitution model that Jerry did,
Gerald教授给你们讲解过
that in an iterative procedure,
在迭代过程中
that state doesn't have to grow.
状态并不需要增长
And in fact, we said it doesn't, so this is an iteration.
因此这是一个迭代过程
But now think about this exact same text
但是如果用正则序语言
if we had a normal-order language.
来运行这段程序
What would happen is
这就会导致
this would no longer be an iterative procedure
这个过程不再是迭代式了
And if you really think about the details of the substitution model,
如果你仔细地思考代换模型
which I'm not going to do here,
在这里我就不细说了
this expression would grow.
这个表达式会不断增长
Why would it grow?
为什么会这样？
It's because when iter calls itself,
因为当ITER调用自己时
it calls itself with this product.
参数是这个乘法表达式
If it's a normal-order language,
而在正则序语言中
that multiplication is not going to get done.
这个乘法并不会在这里求值
That's going to say I'm to call myself
传递给自己并代换的
with a promise to compute this product.
只是这个乘法计算的PROMISE
And now iter goes around again.
然后继续代换下去
And I'm going to call myself
我调用自己
with a promise to compute this product
用的是计算这个乘法的PROMISE
where now one of the one factors is a promise.
但其中的一个因数也是个PROMISE
And I call myself again.
然后我又自调用
And if you write out the substitution model
如果你用代换模型
for that iterative process,
来推演这个迭代步骤
you'll see exactly the same growth in state,
你会发现同样的状态增长
all those promises that are getting remembered
所有的PROMISE都需要被记住
that have to get called in at the very end.
以便在最后被调用
So one of the disadvantages
所以 正则序的缺点之一
is that you can't really express iteration.
就是无法有效地表达迭代
Maybe that's a little theoretical reason why not,
也许这个理由有点偏理论
but in fact, people who are trying to write real operating systems
但事实上 那些使用这类语言来编写
in these languages are running into exactly these types of problems.
实际操作系统的人 也都遇到了这类问题
Like it's perfectly possible to
当然 完全可以
implement a text editor in languages like these.
用这类语言实现一个文本编辑器
But after you work a while,
但是你才用了一会儿
you suddenly have 3 megabytes of stuff,
就发现已经占用了3MB空间
which is-- I guess they call them
我想 那些遇到这类问题的人
the dragging tail problem who are looking at these,
把它叫做 “拖尾问题”
of stuff of promises that sort of haven't been called in
由于不能有效地表达迭代计算
because you couldn't quite express an iteration.
导致堆积了一堆没有被调用的PROMISE
And one of the research questions in these kinds of languages
针对这类语言的一个研究方向就是
are figuring out the right compiler technology
找出一种有效的编译器技术
to get rid of the so-called dragging tails.
来避免这种所谓的“拖尾问题”
It's not simple.
这并不简单
But there's another kind of more striking issue
但是 还有一个很突出的问题
about why you just don't go ahead and make your language normal order.
使你的语言不能变成正则序
And the reason is
问题就在于
that normal-order evaluation and side effects
正则序和副作用
just don't mix.
是不相容的
They just don't go together very well.
它们不能很好地相互配合
Somehow, you can't-
这是因为 你不能
it's sort of you can't simultaneously
你不能一边
go around trying to model objects with local state and change
建模具有局部状态的对象
at the same time
同时又
do these normal-order tricks of de-coupling time.
使用正则序的技巧来解耦时间
Let me just show you a really simple example, very, very simple.
我来举一个非常简单的例子
Suppose we had a normal-order language.
假设语言是正则序求值
And I'm going to start out in this language.
例子是这样的
This is now normal order.
注意现在是正则序求值
I'm going to define x to be 0.
(DEFINE X 0)
It's just some variable I'll initialize.
这只是变量的初始化
And now I'm going to define this little funny function,
现在我要定义一个有趣的函数
which is an identity function.
它就是恒等函数ID
And what it does,
它所做的就是
it keeps track of the last time you called it using x.
用X来记录上一次调用它时N的值
Right? So the identity of n just returns n,
因此(ID N)就返回N
but it sets x to be n.
但还要把X赋值为N
And now I'll define a little increment function,
最后再定义一个过程INC
which is a very little, simple scenario.
也非常简单
Now, imagine I'm interacting with this in the normal-order language,
假设在正则序求值的语言里
and I type the following.
求值下面的表达式
I say define y to be increment the identity function of 3,
我输入 (DEFINE Y (INC (ID 3)))
so y is going to be 4.
因此Y的值应该是4
Now, I say what's x?
X应该是多少呢？
Well, x should have been the value that was remembered last
X应该是最后一次被记住的值
when I called the identity function.
也就是我调用函数ID的时候
So you'd expect to say, well, x is 3 at this point,
你可能会想 这里X应该是3
but it's not.
但是并不是这样
Because when I defined here, y here,
这是因为当我在这里定义Y的时候
what I really defined y to be
Y的真正定义却是
increment of a promise to do this thing.
一个调用函数ID的PROMISE的增量
So I didn't look at y,
因为我没有访问Y
so that identity function didn't get run.
所以ID没有运行
So if I type in this definition
我输入这个定义之后
and look at x, I'm going to get 0.
然后查询X得到的结果是0
Now, if I go look at y and say what's y,
现在 我输入Y查询它的值
say y is 4,
就会得到结果4
looking at y, that very active looking at y
对Y的主动查询
caused the identity function to be run.
会导致ID运行
And now x will get remembered as 3.
现在X=3就被记住
So here x will be 0.
所以上面这里的X就应该是0
Here, x will be 3.
下面这里是3
That's a tiny, little, simple scenario,
这是一个非常简单的场景
but you can see what kind of a mess that's going to make
但你会发现 调试正则序语言
for debugging interactive programs
的交互式程序
when you have normal-order evaluation.
会变得相当混乱
It's very confusing.
很令人迷惑
But it's very confusing for a very deep reason,
导致这样的深层次的原因
which is that the whole idea of putting in delays
也就是引入DELAY的根本理念
is that you throw away time.
是因为我们抛弃了时间的概念
That's why we can have these infinite processes.
也因为如此我们可以处理一些无穷的情况
Since we've thrown away time,
我们抛弃了时间
we don't have to wait for them to run,
就没有必要等它们运行
Right? We decouple the order of events in the computer
我们把计算机中事件发生的顺序
from what we write in our programs.
与程序中的顺序 分离开来
But when we talk about state and set and change,
但是当我们谈及状态、赋值和改变的时候
that's exactly what we do want control of.
这些又都是我们想要控制的
So it's almost as if there's this fundamental contradiction in what you want.
我们的目的有着根本性的矛盾
And that brings us back to these sort of philosophical mutterings
这又让我们进入了一个哲学问题
what is it that you're trying to model
用什么样的模型
and how do you look at the world.
和从什么角度来看这个世界
Or sometimes this is called the
有时这也被称为
the debate over functional programming.
“函数式程序设计的争论”
A so-called purely functional language
所谓的“纯函数式语言”
is one that just doesn't have any side effects.
是完全没有副作用的
Since you have no side effects,
不需要副作用
there's no assignment operator,
也就不需要赋值运算符
so there are no terrible consequences of it.
也就没有什么糟糕的后果
You can use a substitution-like thing.
可以使用类似代换模型
Programs really are like mathematics and not like
程序更像是数学
not like models in the real world, not like objects in the real world.
而不像现实世界中的模型和对象
There are a lot of wonderful things about functional languages.
函数式语言有很多了不起的特性
Since there's no time, you never have any synchronization problems.
没有时间的概念 所以完全不用担心同步的问题
And if you want to put something into a parallel algorithm,
如果你想在并行算法中应用一些东西
you can run the pieces of that parallel processing any way you want.
你可以在这些并行过程中随心所欲地使用
There's just never any synchronization to worry that,
从来不担心同步问题
and it's a very congenial environment for doing this.
在这种环境下这样做是非常方便的
The price is you give up assignment.
代价则是 放弃了赋值
So an advocate of a functional language would say,
函数式语言的支持者会认为
gee, that's just a tiny price to pay.
这点代价算不了什么
You probably shouldn't use assignment most of the time anyway.
在大部分情况下 你都不应该使用赋值
And if you just give up assignment,
如果用你放弃了赋值
you can be in this much, much nicer world
你可以得到一个比对象世界
than this place with objects.
好得多的世界
Well, what's the rejoinder to that?
怎么来反驳这个观点呢？
Remember how we got into this mess.
想想 我们如何走到这一步的
We started trying to model things that had local state.
我们尝试建模具有局部状态的对象
So remember Gerry's random number generator.
想一想Gerald教授给你们讲的随机数生成器
There was this random number generator
这里有一个随机数生成器
that had some little state in it
它内部有一些状态
to compute the next random number
用来计算下一个随机数
and the next random number and the next random number.
下下一个 以及再下一个
And we wanted to hide that state away from the
我们想要把这些状态跟
the Cesaro compute pi process,
计算π的Cesaro算法分离开来
and that's why we needed set!
这就是我们为什么需要赋值
We wanted to package that stated modularly.
我们想要把状态封装在模块中
Well, a functional programming person would say,
函数式语言程序员可能会说
well, you're just all wet.
“你搞错了”
I mean, you can write a perfectly good modular program.
“我的意思是 你能写出另一种更具模块化的程序”
It's just you're thinking about modularity wrong.
“你对模块化的认识并不正确”
You're hung up in this next random number
你太执着于 “生成一个随机数
and the next random number and the next random number.
再生成一个 再生成一个” 这种范式了
Why don't you just say let's write a program.
为什么不写一个这样的程序
Let's write an enumerator
构造一个枚举器
which just generates an infinite stream of random numbers.
它会生成一个随机数的无穷流
We can sort of have that stream all at once,
我们可以立即生成这个流
and that's going to be our source of random numbers.
这样就可以用作随机数的源泉
And then if you like,
如果有需要的话
you can put that through some sort of processor,
你可以把它跟某个处理过程相连
which is-- I don't know-- a Cesaro test,
比如说Cesaro测试
and that can do what it wants.
然后这个处理过程进行自己的计算
And what would come out of there
从这里出来的则是
would be a stream of successive approximations to pi.
其中是一串的对π的估计值组成的流
So as we looked further down this stream,
随着我们深入访问这个流
we'd tug on this Cesaro thing,
相当于去拽这个Cesaro盒子
and it would pull out more and more random numbers.
它就会拉取出许多随机数
And the further and further we look down the stream,
随着我们对流的深入访问
the better an approximation we'd get to pi.
得到的对π的估计值就越准
And it would do exactly the same as the other computation,
具体的计算过程还是一样的
except we're thinking about the modularity different.
只不过使用了另一种模块化的方式
We're saying imagine we had all that
我们可以想象成一下子
infinite streams of random numbers all at once.
就有了这所有的随机数
You can see the details of this procedure in the book.
这个过程的细节在书上有
But similarly, there are other things that we tend to get locked into
我们同样也陷于另外一些类似的事情中
on this one and that one and the next one and the next one,
这种关于 这个、下一个以及再下一个的范式
which don't have to be that way.
完全可以不这么来做
Like you might think about like a banking system,
我们来思考一下银行系统
which is a very simple idea.
有个非常简单的场景
Imagine we have a program that sort of represents a bank account.
我们假设这个程序代表了银行帐户
The bank account might have in it--
银行账户中可能有
if we looked at this in a sort of message-passing view of the world,
如果我们以消息传递的角度来看
we'd say a bank account is an object
我们认为银行账户是一个对象
that has some local state in there, which is the balance, say.
内部保存着标识余额的局部状态BALANCE
And a user using this system comes
如果一个用户使用这个系统
and sends a transaction request.
发出交易请求
So the user sends a transaction request,
用户发出的交易请求可能是
like deposit some money,
存一些钱
and the bank account maybe--
银行账户就会
let's say the bank account always responds with what the current balance is.
我们假设银行账户总是以当前余额作为回应
The user says let's deposits some money,
用户存了一些钱
and the bank account sends back a message which is the balance.
银行账户就会返回一个消息指明当前余额
And the user says deposit some more,
用户再存一些钱
and the bank account sends back a message.
银行就再返回消息
And just like the random number generating
就像生成随机数一样
you'd say, gee, we would like to use set.
我们想使用赋值来实现
We'd like to have balance be a piece of local state inside this bank account
帐户的内部保存了局部状态BALANCE
because we want to separate the state of the user
因为我们想要把用户状态
from the state of the bank account.
和银行账户的状态分离开来
Well, that's the message-processing view.
这是从消息传递的角度来看
There's a stream view with that thing,
如果从流的角度来看
which does the same thing without any set or side effects.
不需要赋值或副作用就可以达到同样的效果
And the idea is again
再次强调 想法是这样的
we don't think about anything having local state.
我们认为它们都没有局部状态
We think about the bank account as something
我们把银行账户看作是
that's going to process a stream of transaction requests.
能够处理一系列交易请求的东西
So think about this bank account not
不把银行账户看做
as something that goes message by message,
逐个消息地处理
but something that takes in a stream of transaction requests
而是处理某种交易请求流的东西
like maybe successive deposit announced.
这个请求流可能是一些列的存款声明
1, 2, 2, 4, those might be successive amounts to deposit.
比如 1 2 2 4 这样的连续存钱请求
And then coming out of it is the successive balances 1, 3, 5, 9.
从帐户出来的流应该是 1 3 5 9
So we think of the bank account not as something that has state,
我们不把银行账户看做某种具有状态的东西
but something that acts
而是某种能够处理
sort of on the infinite stream of requests.
有关请求的无穷流的东西
But remember, we've thrown away time.
但要注意 我们抛弃了时间
So what we can do is if the user's here,
如果这里有一个用户
we can have this infinite stream of requests
这个无穷请求流的元素
being generated one at a time coming from the user
我们可以一次生成一个
and this transaction stream
而这个交易流
coming back on a printer being printed one at a time.
则会逐个打印在屏幕上
And if we drew a little line here,
如果在这里画一条线
right there to the user,
就在这里
the user couldn't tell that this system doesn't have state.
对用户来说 他根本无法分辨
that this system doesn't have state.
这个系统是否有内部状态
It looks just like the other one,
这个跟消息传递那种是一样的
but there's no state in there.
只不过这个没有状态
And by the way,
哦 顺便提一下
just to show you, here's an actual implementation
这是具体的代码实现
of this-- we'll call it make deposit account
我们把它叫做MAKE-DEPOSIT-ACCOUNT
because you can only deposit.
因为它只能够存钱
It takes an initial balance
这个过程接受一个初始余额
and then a stream of deposits you might make.
以及一个可能发起的存款流
And what is it?
具体怎么做呢？
Well, it's just cons-stream of the balance
它只是用CONS-STREAM把余额BALANCE
onto make a new account stream
和一个新的存款账户流组合在一起
whose initial balance
新存款流的初始余额
is the old balance plus the first thing in the deposit stream
就是之前BALANCE的值加上存款流的第一个元素
whose rest, right and,
而其余部分则是
make deposit account works on the rest of which is the tail of the deposit stream.
存款流的尾部分
So there's sort of a very typical message-passing,
因此这种非常典型的消息传递式、面向对象的问题
message-passing, object-oriented thing that's done without side effects at all.
完全可以不用副作用来解决
There are very many things you can do this way.
很多地方都可以这样做
Well, can you do everything without assignment?
那么 我们可以完全不用赋值么？
Can everybody go over to purely functional languages?
可以只用纯函数式语言吗？
Well, we don't know,
这个问题谁也说不清
but there seem to be places
好像有些地方
where purely functional programming breaks down.
纯函数式语言无法派上用场
Where it starts hurting is when you have things like this,
当遇到像这样的系统时 问题就变得棘手起来
but you also mix it up with
特别是当你
the other things that we had to worry that,
还需要考虑其它因素的时候
which are objects and sharing
有关对象和共享
and two independent agents being the same.
以及两个独立的主体共享同一个东西
So under a typical one,
举一个典型的例子
suppose you want to extend this bank account.
假如你来扩展这个帐户
So here's a bank account.
这是一个帐户
Bank accounts take in a stream of transaction requests
帐户接受一个交易请求流
and put out streams of, say, balances or responses to that.
输出的流则是关于余额的回复
But suppose you want to model the fact
假设你所建模的是联合账户
that this is a joint bank account between two independent people.
而由两个独立用户共享
Right? I don't know. So suppose there are two people,
我们假设 假设有两个人
say, Bill and Dave,
比如说Bill和Dave
who have a joint bank account.
他们俩共享一个帐户
How would you model this?
怎么来建模呢？
Well, you might, Bill puts out a stream of transaction requests,
你或许会让Bill输出一个交易请求流
and Dave puts out a stream of transaction requests,
Dave也产生一个这样的流
and somehow, they have to merge into this bank account.
这两个流需要以某种方式合并到银行账户中
So what you might do is write a little stream
因此你需要编写一个MERGE过程
processing thing called merge,
来处理这些流
which sort of takes these, merges them together,
它把这些流合并在一起
produces a single stream for the bank account.
形成单个流 送入银行账户
Now they're both talking to the same bank account.
现在他们就共享一个帐户了
That's all great, but how do you write merge?
看起来不错 问题是怎么来实现MERGE
What, What's this procedure merge?
MERGE怎么来合并？
You want to do something that's reasonable.
需要合理的合并依据
Your first guess might be to say,
你可能首先会想
well, we'll take alternate requests from Bill and Dave.
我们从Bill和Dave中选一个请求来处理
But what happens if But what happens if suddenly in the middle thing
但是如果在这中途
Dave goes away on vacation for two years?
Dave突然外出度假两年 会怎么样？
Then Bill's sort of stuck.
Bill的交易就完全被阻塞了
So what you want to do is-- well, it's hard to describe.
你想要的是
What you want to do is what people call fair merge.
是一种公平的合并
The idea of fair merge is
这个所谓公平的合并
is it sort of should do them alternately,
应该是交替地一次处理一个
but if there's nothing waiting here,
但是如果一个人没有了交易
it should take one twice.
应该继续去处理另一个人的交易
Notice I can't even say that without talking about time.
但是没有时间 我就不能这样做
So one of the other active researcher areas in functional languages
函数式语言的另一个活跃研究领域就是
is inventing little things like fair merge
发明类似于“公平合并”的算法
maybe some others,
又或者是其它的东西
which will take the places where I used to need side effects and objects
用于取代原来需要副作用和对象的地方
and sort of hide them away in some very well-defined modules of the system
用一种良好定义的模块化系统来隐藏它们
so that all the problems of assignment
这样 系统中就不会到处产生
don't sort of leak out all over the system but
赋值所带来的问题
are captured in some fairly well-understood things.
因为它可以被理解透彻的概念所描述
More generally, I think what you're seeing
推而广之 我想你们也发现了
is that we're running across
我们正面对 我所认为的
what I think is a very basic problem in computer science,
计算机科学中最基本的问题
which is how to
也就是
how to define languages that somehow can talk about delayed evaluation
我们如何定义一门支持延迟求值的语言
But also
但同时又能够
be able to reflect this view that there are objects in the world.
又能够把事物看做对象来操作
How do we somehow get both?
怎么样才能两者兼有之？
And I think that's a very hard problem.
我认为这个问题很困难
And it may be that it's a very hard problem
但是这个很困难的问题
that has almost nothing to do with computer science,
却和计算机科学的关系不大
that it really is a problem having to do with
它真正涉及的是
two very incompatible ways of looking at the world.
两种不相容的看待世界的方式
OK, questions?
有问题吗？
AUDIENCE: You mentioned earlier that
学生：你之前提到过
once you introduce assignment,
一旦引入了赋值
the general rule for using the substitution model is you can't.
就不能使用代换模型了
Unless you're very careful, you can't.
除非你非常小心
PROFESSOR: Right.
教授：对的
AUDIENCE: Is there a set of techniques or a set of guidelines
学生：有什么技术或者指导方针
for localizing the effects of assignment
来确定赋值的影响
so that the very careful becomes defined?
以便说清楚这个“很小心”是怎么回事吗？
PROFESSOR: I don't know. Um...
教授：我不知道
Let me think.
我想想
Well, certainly, there was an assignment inside memo proc,
当然 实现MEM-PROC也使用了赋值
but that was sort of hidden away.
但是它被隐藏了起来
It ended up not making any difference.
因为它没有对结果造成影响
Part of the reason for that is once this thing triggered
部分原因之一在于 一旦触发这个过程
that it had run and gotten an answer,
它被求值并得到结果
that answer will never change.
这个结果不会再变化
So that was sort of a one-time assignment.
有点像单次赋值
So one very general thing you can do
一个一般性原则就是
is if you only do what's called a one-time assignment
如果你只用这种单次赋值
and never change anything,
并且它不再改变
then you can do better.
我想应该不会有太大问题
One of the problems in this merge thing, people have--
还有一个问题在于MERGE --
people have-- let me see if this is right.
让我想想对不对
I think it's true that with fair merge,
我认为有了公平合并这一技术
with just fair merge, you can begin effectively simulating
你可以在语言的其它地方
assignment in the rest of the language.
有效地模拟赋值
It seems like anything you do to go outside--
这就像为了解决问题你会引入一些东西
I'm not quite sure that's true for fair merge,
我不清楚对公平合并来说是否成立
but it's true of a little bit more general things that people have been doing.
但是对人们正在尝试的一些一般性事情是成立的
So it might be that any little bit you put in,
所以 这可能是你引入的这一点点东西
suddenly if they allow you to build arbitrary stuff,
突然间 使你能构建任何东西
it's almost as bad as having assignment altogether.
这就几乎跟有了赋值一样糟糕了
But that's an area that people are thinking about now.
这也是人们在研究的一个领域
AUDIENCE: I guess I don't see the problem here with merge
学生：我还没有太明白MERGE的问题
if, you know the sense, I call Bill, if Bill is a procedure,
如果我调用Bill它是个过程
then Bill is going to increment the bank account
那么Bill就会增加银行账户
or build the list that 's going to put in the next element.
或者创建一个表 用于放置下一个存款
If I call Dave twice in a row, that will do that.
如果我连续调用Dave两次 他肯定也会那样
I'm not sure where fair merge has to be involved.
我并不清楚为什么需要公平合并
PROFESSOR: The problem is imagine these really as people.
教授：关键在于你得把这些当作真人一样
See, here I have the user who's interacting with this bank account.
这里有一个用户在操作帐户
Put in a request, get an answer. Put in a request, get an answer.
请求一次 得到结果
AUDIENCE: Right.
学生：对
PROFESSOR: But if the only way I can process request
教授：如果我只能通过从两个流中选择一个
is to alternate them from two people--
来处理请求的话
AUDIENCE: Well, why would you alternate them?
学生：为什么要二选一呢？
PROFESSOR: Why don't I?
教授：为什么不呢？
AUDIENCE: Yes. Why do you?
学生：对啊 为什么要这样呢？
PROFESSOR: Think of them as real people, right?
教授：假设这些是现实中的人 对吗？
This guy might go away for a year.
这个人外出一年
And you're sitting here at the bank account window,
你只能在银行账户窗口旁边等待
and you can't put in two requests
就是不能处理两个请求
because it's waiting for this guy.
因为你还得等这个人
AUDIENCE: Why does it have to be waiting for one?
学生：为什么非得等他呢？
PROFESSOR: Because it's trying to compute a function.
教授：因为这里是在计算一个函数
I have to define a function.
我必须定义一个函数
Another way to say that
换种方式来说
is the answer to what comes out of this merge box
这个MERGE盒子的输出
is not a function of what goes in.
并不是输入的函数
Because, see, what would the function be?
明白了吗？再来看看这个MERGE是怎么运行的
Suppose he puts in 1, 1, 1, 1,
假设Bill输入 1 1 1 1
and he puts in 2, 2, 2, 2.
Dave输入2 2 2 2
What's the answer supposed to be?
MERGE应该输出什么呢？
It's not good enough to say it's 1, 2, 1, 2, 1, 2.
这里并不一定是 1 2 1 2 1 2
AUDIENCE: I understand.
学生：我明白了
But when Bill puts in 1, 1 goes in.
当Bill输入1 1也就进去了
When Dave puts in 2, twice 2 goes in twice.
Dave再输入两个2 MERGE就输出两个2
AUDIENCE: When Bill puts in--
学生：当Bill输入
PROFESSOR: Right.
教授：对的
AUDIENCE: Why can't it be hooked to the time of the input--
学生：为什么不能在输入的数据上
the actual procedural--
加上时间信息呢？
PROFESSOR: Because I don't have time.
教授：因为这里没有时间这个概念
See, all I can say is I'm going to define a function.
我只是定义一个函数
I don't have time.
没有时间概念
There's no concept if it's going to alternate,
如果是二选一的话
except if nobody's there, it's going to wait a while for him.
如果选中的流没有人 就得等待它
It's just going to say I have the stream of requests,
它只会说 我有一个请求流
the timeless infinite streams
这是是Dave生成的
of all the requests that Dave would have made, right?
没有时刻的、无穷长度的请求流
And the timeless infinite stream of all the requests Bill would have made,
Bill可能生成 没有时刻的无穷请求流
and I want to operate on them.
我想对这些东西做运算
See, that's how this bank account is working.
这就是银行帐户的工作原理
And the problem is
问题是
that these poor people who are sitting at the bank account windows
这些坐在银行窗口前的倒霉蛋们
have the misfortune to exist in time.
来得并不是时候
They don't see their infinite stream
它们才看不到这个无穷流
of all the requests they would have ever made.
什么时候其中会有请求
They're waiting now, and they want an answer.
他们只是等着 等待帐户的响应
So if you're sitting there--
假设你坐在屏幕前
if this is the screen operation on some time-sharing system
操作着一台分时系统的计算机
and it's working functionally,
而且它还是函数式的
you want an answer then when you talk the character.
输入指令后你就希望看到结果
You don't want it to have to wait for everybody in the whole system
但是你并不想主机在处理完所有其它人的命令
to have typed one character before it can get around to service you.
之后再来处理你的命令
So that's the problem.
这就是问题所在
I mean, the fact that people live in time, apparently.
我的意思就是 用户的世界当然是存在时间概念的
If they didn't, it wouldn't be a problem.
如果没有 这就不构成问题
AUDIENCE: I'm afraid I miss the point of
学生：我想我还是不太理解
having no time in this banking transaction.
银行交易中为什么没有时间概念这一要点
Isn't time very important?
难道时间不是非常重要吗？
For instance, the sequence of events.
举例说 有一系列事件
As if, If Dave take out $100, and then
比如Dave取款$100
then the timing sequence should be important.
这些顺序应该很重要才对
How do you treat transactions as streams?
你怎么能把它们看作是流呢？
PROFESSOR: Well, that's the thing I'm saying.
教授：这就是我一直在强调的
This is an example where you can't.
在这个例子中确实做不到那一点
You can't.
做不到
What goes, The point is what comes out of here
关键在于 这里的输出
is simply not a function of the stream going in here
并不是这两个输入流
going in here and the stream going in here.
的函数
It's a function of the stream going in here
这个函数跟这个输入流有关
and the stream going in here
还跟这个输入流有关
and some kind of information about time,
还包括某种有关时间的信息
which is precisely what a normal-order language won't let you say.
这也正是正则序语言不想让你知道的
AUDIENCE: In order to brings this back into a more functional perspective,
学生：为了让这个系统更加函数式
could we just explicitly time stamp all the inputs from Bill and Dave
我们能不能把Bill和Dave的交易请求附上时间戳
and define fair merge to just be the sort on those time stamps?
而使用时间戳作为公平合并的依据？
PROFESSOR: Yeah, you can do that.
教授：当然 当然可以
You can do that sort of thing.
你可以那样做
Another thing you could say is imagine
或者 我们可以这样来想象
that really what this function is,
我们把这个函数看作是
is that it does a read every microsecond,
MERGE每毫秒读一次输入
and then if there's none there,
如果没有读到东西
that's considered an empty one.
就认为没有请求
That's about equivalent to what you said.
这和你刚刚说的那种方式是等价的
And yes, you can do that, but that's a glitch.
当然可以这样做 但有点旁门左道
So it's not quite only implementation we're worried about.
我们不只是关心函数的具体实现
We're worried about expressive power in the language,
我们关心的是语言的表达力
and what we're running across is a real mismatch
我们遇到的困难是
between what we can say easily and what we'd like to say.
我们不能很容易地表达我们想要表达的东西
AUDIENCE: It sounds like where we're getting hung up with that
学生：听起来好像如果两个人同时发出请求
one input from both Bill and Dave at the same time.
这个方法就会出问题
PROFESSOR: It's not quite one, but it's anything you define.
教授：并不只是这个 只要是你定义的都可能出问题
So you can say Dave can go twice as often,
你当然可以说Dave经常发起两个请求
but if anything you predefine,
但是你如果预先定义了什么
it's not the right thing.
这样做也不正确
You can't decide at some particular function of their input requests.
你不能确定某些特定函数的输入请求
Worse yet, I mean, worse yet,
但是还有更坏的情况
there are things that even merge can't do.
有一些情况甚至MERGE也处理不了
One thing you might want to do that's even more general is suddenly
比如突然有一天你想要
you add somebody else to this bank account system.
把另一个人关联在这个银行帐户上
You go and you add John to this bank account system.
假如这个人是John
And now there's yet another stream that's going to come into the picture
现在图上就要多一个流
at some time which we haven't prespecified.
在一个我们未曾指定的时候
So that's something even fair merge can't do,
这种情况甚至公平合并也无法给出合理的合并
and they're things called-- I forget-- manager or something.
还需要有MANAGER一类的东西
That's a generalization of fair merge to allow that.
需要一种更一般性的公平合并来解决
There's a whole sort of research discipline saying
有很多研究都在讨论
how far can you push this functional perspective
通过不断引入新机制
by adding more and more mechanism?
函数式思维能应用到哪种程度？
And how far does that go before the whole thing breaks down
在我们不得不使用赋值之前
and you might as well been using set anyway.
函数式程序设计能干成什么样？
AUDIENCE: But not automatic deposit.
学生：看来自动存款就不行
PROFESSOR: OK, thank you.
教授：好的 下课
MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
本项目主页
https://github.com/DeathKing/Learning-SICP